Hi, in this part I’m going to show
you how Perl can compare scalar values.
I would like to see whether 1 and 1.0 and 1.00
Are they equal, one of them is bigger, one of them is smaller?
What about 1.00 in a string, so in quotation marks?
What about comparing “foo” and “bar,” these two strings?
So Perl has—
We saw that in Perl there are operators like “+” and “.”, they convert
strings to numbers and numbers to strings depending on their own context.
And they don’t care what the actual value you put in the variables.
This is similar with the operators.
Perl actually has two sets of comparison operators.
And I put here in this separate file a table so you can see there
is a set of numeric comparisons and a set of string comparisons.
Equal equal the check that the two sides are equal as numbers.
And eq will check whether they are equal as strings.
And this would checks whether they are not equal, this would
check that the left hand side is smaller as numbers.
And less than would compare them as strings.
So let’s see how that works.
Let’s have an example here.
Let’s compare to 12 to 12.0.
And if that’s true, print out true.
Else print out false.
00:01:44.1,00:01:49
So if I run this code I’ll get true
because 12 is equal to 12.
And Perl disregards the dot zero because even though I’m writing here in
floating poin notation, that’s still only 12 as the real value.
The same would happen if I put here two zero’s,
it doesn’t really matter, I still get true.
And if I put here, this in quotes, that would be still true
because Perl compares the string to a number, and gets the same.
Now if I compare them with using eq and I run the script, then
I get false, because now Perl converts this number into a string.
So you get 12 on left-hand side and
12 dot zero zero on right-hand side.
Two strings and they are not equal as strings.
What about comparing numbers?
Which one is smaller, which one is bigger?
So let’s compare two to three.
Obviously two is smaller than three and I
get true as you can see here.
So two is smaller than three.
What if I compare them as strings?
That’s the same, its two.
Still true because two is before three in the ascii table.
And what happens if I’m comparing twelve to three?
Well that’s obvious.
It’s true because twelve is bigger than three.
But what if I am comparing with greater than, the string comparison?
Then I run it and I get false.
So it might be surprising to some people but if you think about it, the way this compares “gt” compares, or all the
string comparisons compare is they take the first character which is one, comparing this to the first character here which is three.
And by this character already we know that the left hand side
happens before the right hand side in the ascii table.
So by the point it will decide the twelve as a string is
smaller than three and because of that this expression returns false.
So what happens when I compare “foo” to “bar.”
Whether I’m checking whether they are equal with two equal signs.
And I run this and surprisingly it gives me true.
It might be less surprising to those who know that what does it mean.
So “==” compares the two sides as numbers.
And converts them as numbers and that’s the reason we get these warnings.
Because the “==” sign is expecting two numbers.
There are two strings which are not exact
numbers, so Perl gives me a warning.
And converts both sides to zero because it will try to convert
try to look at the left-hand side, look for numbers.
There are no numbers in either of the strings
so they both equal to 0.
And therefore 0 equals to 0 as two numbers and that’s
true, so that’s the reason Perl prints here true.
Obviously if you know that you need to compare two things
that might be strings, then you probably used “eq.”
Actually in most places of the world you probably used “eq”
when you were comparing the two strings, the two values.
So in this case this we obviously get the false as I expected.
Something that might be more interesting, that even if I compare with
empty string, I get the same problem or same issue.
I get this true and I get these two warnings.
Now just to remind you, I get those
warnings, because I asked for those warnings.
So it’s pretty important to use that pragma, otherwise this would silently just
be true and be very surprising for most of the people.
Obviously here too if I’m using “eq” that would be okay running
the script would give me the false as I expected.
Now let’s see one example where this problem might appear.
So, your name let’s say I’m printing out a question
and I’m accepting some string from the command line.
Then I’m chomping off the new line from the end and
I’m checking whether the main name is equal to 0.
And that’s a common mistake some people make who don’t
know about the difference between “eq” and “==.”
So if I type here some string, then I
get all these warnings, but I get true.
Even though what I was checking, I was
checking whether it was an empty string.
And I get true because this string, “ddd” looking at
the left-hand side is 0 as a number
Equal equal converts to number.
The right-hand side is equal to number.
So the two sides are equal.
The right thing would be obvious to check whether this
eq whether the string is an empty string.
So then I can run this code and say “ddd” and that’s false.
And on the other hand if I run this script and then press enter without
typing anything, then it’s true because now the result is an empty string.
So that’s about comparing values.
Thank you for watching, and see you next time.